A Finding Aid to the Arnold Newman Photographs of Artists, 1940-1961, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Arnold Newman photographs of artists
1940-1961
Archives of American Art
Newman, Arnold, 1918-2006
AAA.newmarno
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The collection of photographs of artists by Arnold Newman measures 0.6 linear feet and dates from 1940 to 1961. The collection consists of photographs of various artists taken by Newman. Some of the represented artists include: Gertrude Abercrombie, Julius Bloch, Willem De Kooning, David Hare, Joseph Kaplan, Ibram Lassaw, and Joseph Stella. Folders consist of a large version photograph and both a duplicate small version and transparency of the photograph.
Biographical / Historical
Arnold Newman (1918-2006) was a photographer based primarily in New York. Arnold Newman was born March 3, 1918 in New York City. He was raised and attended schools in Atlantic City, N.J. and Miami Beach, FL. He studied art under a scholarship at the University of Miami, Coral Gables, FL from 1936 to 1938. He died in New York City on June 6, 2006. Generally acknowledged as the pioneer of the environmental portrait, he is also known for his still life and abstract photography, and he is considered as one of the most influential photographers of the 20th Century.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series.
Series 1: Arnold Newman Photographs of Artists, 1940-1960 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Scope and Contents
The collection of photographs of artists by Arnold Newman measures 0.6 linear feet and dates from 1940 to 1961. The collection consists of photographs of various artists taken by Newman. Some of the represented artists include: Gertrude Abercrombie, Julius Bloch, Willem De Kooning, David Hare, Joseph Kaplan, Ibram Lassaw, and Joseph Stella. Folders consist of a large version photograph and both a duplicate small version and transparency of the photograph.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Microfilmed materials must be consulted on microfilm. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1961 by Arnold Newman.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 153 & 1027 available at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York
- AAA.newmarno holdings, Archival Resource Key
  - AAA - microfilm ILL- no restrictions, Archival Resource Key (Reel 0153.newman)
  - AAA - microfilm ILL- Duplicate, Archival Resource Key (Reel 0153.newman c2)
  - AAA - microfilm ILL- no restrictions, Archival Resource Key (Reel 1027.newman)
- Arnold Newman Photographs of Artists, 1940-1961; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  The collection of photographs of artists by Arnold Newman measures 0.6 linear feet and dates from 1940 to 1961. The collection consists of photographs of various artists taken by Newman. Some of the represented artists include: Gertrude Abercrombie, Julius Bloch, Willem De Kooning, David Hare, Joseph Kaplan, Ibram Lassaw, and Joseph Stella. Folders consist of a large version photograph and both a duplicate small version and transparency of the photograph.
  - Gertrude Abercrombie, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Josef Albers, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ivan Le Lorraine Albright, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Milton Avery, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Peggy Bacon, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William Baziotes, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ludwig Bemmelmans, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boris Blai, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Julius Bloch, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Henry Botkin, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alexander Brook, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charles Burchfield, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - David Burliuk, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alexander Calder, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Federico Castellon, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nikolai Cikovsky, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Francis Criss, 1944-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jo Davidson, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stuart Davis, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Philip Evergood, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lyonel Feininger, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Richard Florsheim, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - William Gropper, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chaim Gross, 1942, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - John Groth, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Louis Gugliemi, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philip Guston, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Robert Gwathmey, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - David Hare, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Morris Hirschfield, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hans Hofmann, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Edward Hopper, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Paul Jenkins, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mervin Jules, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Morris Kantor, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Joseph Kaplan, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Karl Knaths, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Willem De Kooning, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Leon Kroll, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Yasuo Kuniyoshi, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ibram Lassaw, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Robert Laurent, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jacob Lawrence, 1944, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Julian Levi, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jack Levine, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jacques Lipchitz, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Charles Sheeler, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Joseph Stella, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)